http://uk.linkedin.com/in/willbutterworth 25 Simpson Street, London, SW11 3HN Mobile: +44 (0) 7790552198

WILL BUTTERWORTH, MBA

Strategy Lead & Head of Strategic Operations, EMEA

Profile

I'm an MBA graduate with over 10 years' experience in strategic leadership. With effectiveness at the heart of my approach, my work has been a proven growth driver for local and global brands across a variety of sectors including food and retail. I am currently Strategy Director and Operations Lead for EMEA Strategy at Edelman, the global integrated communications firm, where I oversee the development and delivery of strategic projects for the firms' major clients in EMEA. I recently received an MBA with distinction from Warwick University Business School where I focused my research project on how brand building accelerates growth in scale-up organisations. I'm an adaptable brand builder with a strong track record of delivering award-winning creative for major brands. It's my versatility that I'm most proud of and, as our industry converges, I believe I've developed a critical skill set that adds value to any business I partner with.

Strengths

- Strategic and Creative Leadership
- Brand Building
- Collaboration across Matrixed Organisations
- Operational Excellence
- ⊕ Marketing Effectiveness

Employment History

Edelman

Strategy Lead & Head of Operations, EMEA Strategy June 2022 – Present

After being headhunted in 2020 I'm leading strategy for three of the agencies highest billing EMEA clients: Starbucks, ASICS, and Microsoft. In 2022 I was promoted to the EMEA Leadership Council where I've been responsible for operationalising the 38 strategists across the EMEA region.

ASICS: Challenging the world to a race without a finish line (Sport Grand Prix Winner Cannes Lions 2021)

- As running shoe brands previously known more for fashion than performance began to make technological advancements, key running audiences no longer saw ASICS as the clear winner in the running category
- Most brands focus on celebrating whoever crosses the finish line first. To challenge this, we wanted to show that what really separates us from the competition is our mindset. With this in mind, we created the Eternal Run, a race without a finish line. We invited 23 athletes, influencers, and journalists with varied running abilities to the Bonneville Salt Flats in Utah.

Edelman Strategy Director June 2020 – June 2022

KLM: Can sustainability play an additive role for an airline brand?

- Designed and developed the largest ever creative-led project in the EMEA region to help KLM understand and operationalise the role sustainability plays in brand and communications in a hard to abate industry.
- Global mixed methodology research involving qual ethnography, quantitative analysis of five permission space territories in eight markets, leading multiple C-team workshops to operationalise findings within the business.
- A specific focus for the project was helping the C-team navigate the relationship between a sustainability-focused corporate strategy and how that can show up in consumer facing environments.

Leo Burnett Creative Strategy Director June 2018 – June 2020

McDonald's UK: The restaurant where we all come as we are

- In 2018 I joined the McDonald's team at Leo Burnett focusing on brand leadership across the portfolio.
- Under my stewardship we stemmed a decline in brand affinity through a brand building approach that recognised the democratic and welcoming role the brand played during a time of national disunity.
- My first promo campaign saw McNuggets growth increase by 10% with a sales contribution of +0.2%.
- I've repositioned the value range, shifting from the beloved 'like getting your money's worth' to 'a little means a lot' in response to a change in consumer sentiment around value.
- In the Food and Beverage space I developed a new innovation process for limited time offer windows as well as the
 Monopoly campaign Peely-Peely which brought a new distinctive brand asset to the business.

25 Simpson Street, London, SW11 3HN Mobile: +44 (0) 7790552198

Karmarama Senior Creative Strategist November 2014 – June 2018

Honda: Challenging Britain's petrol heads to a race like no other

- DMA silver winning campaign where I challenged petrol heads to prove they had what it takes to tame Type-R.
- ⊕ I developed a multi-channel campaign ecosystem including app & website to captured racers' details & trigger an automated conversion programme.
- The campaign sold 75% of target in the first two months with a ROMI level for 39.7 & 81% increase in test drives.

AO.com: It takes superhuman endeavour to get customers what they need when they need it

- ⊕ In 2017 I re-launched the AO brand in the UK, paving the way for its next stage of growth.
- I developed the brand platform *Delivering Tomorrow*, to leverage the biggest customer need in the market and reinforce AO's credentials as a lead innovator in the sector.
- The brand re-launch beat all targets, most importantly it increased trust and spontaneous awareness by 4% & 5% respectively. In year one the campaign delivered a ROMI of £4.57 based on a £30 million investment.

Plusnet: Telling the story of staff who just can't help but help

- DMA Gold winning campaign for digital campaigning
- Responsible for eCRM, brand and performance marketing strategy over a two-year period that saw Plusnet reach
 1 million customers for the first time in their history.
- ⊕ I created their best ever performing brand campaign with *Made that Way*. This helped the business maintain a positive eSOV while increasing consideration & sp. awareness both by 4%, leading to a ROMI of £5.67.
- Led the annual marketing planning process, managing all client stakeholders including board level. Developed all brand plans for 2015 and 2016 and TTL platform 'Can't help but help' to integrate social, CRM & brand plans.

The Value Engineers

 Intern
 Summer 2008

 Analyst
 Dec 2009 – May 2011

 Strategy Consultant
 Jun 2011 – Nov 2014

Electronic Arts: Global Digital Strategy Development & European Gamer Segmentation

- Worked alongside the global insights team, providing them with analysis required to understand the needs of gamers across a multi-channel purchase journey.
- Worked to develop a single digital and data strategy project for the entire organization at a Global level to help them reach 2012 target of \$1 billion in digital revenues.

Selected Creative Output

Honda: Green Hell McDonald's The Wedding McDonald's Monopoly: Peely-Peely McDonald's: Value McDonald's: Big Mac Debate McDonald's: Time Well Spent McDonald's: Longer with what you love AO.com: Delivering Tomorrow Plusnet: Can't Help But Help Plusnet: Skip button Unibet: #luckisnocoincidence Bet Victor: Embrace the Unpredictable

Education

Warwick University Business School Master of Business Administration (MBA) with Distinction Research Study: How brand building accelerates growth in scale-ups (Distinction)

2021-2023

Cardiff University
Journalism BA Hons 2:1

2006-2009

Dr Challoner's Grammar School, Amersham A-Levels AAB 10 GCSE's A-C 1998-2005

Skills and interests

Sport and exercise lover, keen endurance athlete. I love cycling and have completed two Ironman to date. Unfortunately, the state of my knees is not making another one likely any time soon.

References available on request.